Let's go south.
دعونا نتجه جنوباً.
All of you are actually going south.
جميعكم في الحقيقة متجه جنوباً.
This is the direction of south, this way,
هذا هو اتجاه الجنوب، من هنا،
and if you go 8,000 kilometers out of the back of this room,
وإذا انطلقت لمسافة 8000 كيلومتر خلف هذه الغرفة،
you will come to as far south as you can go anywhere on Earth,
سوف تصل إلى أقصى ما يمكنك أن تصل إليه في جنوب الأرض،
the Pole itself.
القطب بذاته.
Now, I am not an explorer.
أنا لست مستكشفاً.
I'm not an environmentalist.
ولست من مناصري البيئة.
I'm actually just a survivor,
في الحقيقة أنا مجرد ناجٍ،
and these photographs that I'm showing you here are dangerous.
وهذه الصور التي أعرضها لكم هنا هي صور خطيرة.
They are the ice melt of the South and North Poles.
إنها صور ذوبان جليد القطبين الجنوبي والشمالي.
And ladies and gentlemen,
سيداتي سادتي،
we need to listen to what these places are telling us,
علينا أن نستمع لما تخبرنا به هذه الأماكن،
and if we don't, we will end up with our own survival situation
وإن لم نفعل ذلك، علينا أن نواجه تحدي النجاة
here on planet Earth.
هنا على كوكب الأرض.
I have faced head-on these places,
لقد واجهتُ هذه الأماكن وجهاً لوجه،
and to walk across a melting ocean of ice
وأن تمشي على محيط جليدي آخذ بالذوبان
is without doubt the most frightening thing
هو بلا شك أكثر شيء مرعب
that's ever happened to me.
حصل لي على الإطلاق.
Antarctica is such a hopeful place.
القارة القطبية الجنوبية هي مكان مفعم بالأمل إلى حد بعيد.
It is protected by the Antarctic Treaty, signed in 1959.
وهي محمية بمعاهدة القطب الجنوبي الموقعة عام 1959.
In 1991, a 50-year agreement was entered into
أضيف إليها في عام 1991 اتفاقية مدتها 50 عام
that stops any exploitation in Antarctica,
تمنع أي محاولة لاستغلال القطب الجنوبي،
and this agreement could be altered,
وهذه الاتفاقية يمكن أن تعدل،
changed, modified, or even abandoned
تغير أو تستبدل، أو حتى أن يترك العمل بها
starting in the year 2041.
بدءاً من العام 2041.
Ladies and gentlemen,
سيداتي سادتي،
people already far up north from here in the Arctic
هناك أناس حالياً إلى أقصى الشمال من هنا في القطب الشمالي
are already taking advantage
بدؤوا باستغلال
of this ice melt,
ذوبان الجليد هذا،
taking out resources from areas already that have been covered in ice
يستخرجون الموارد من أماكن بقيت مغطاة بالجليد
for the last 10, 20, 30,000,
لـ 10، 20، 30 ألف،
100,000 years.
100 ألف عام.
Can they not join the dots
أليس بإمكانهم معرفة السبب
and think, "Why is the ice actually melting?"
وأن يفكروا، "لماذا يذوب الجليد؟"
This is such an amazing place,
إنه حقاً مكان مدهش،
the Antarctic, and I have worked hard
القطب الجنوبي، ولقد عملت جاهداً
for the last 23 years on this mission
خلال الـ 23 عاماً الماضية على هذه المهمة
to make sure that what's happening up here in the North
لأحرص على ألا يتكرر ما يحصل في الشمال
does never happen, cannot happen in the South.
وأن أمنع حدوثه في الجنوب.
Where did this all begin?
مين أين بدأ كل هذا؟
It began for me at the age of 11.
بدأ الأمر بالنسبة لي في عمر الحادية عشرة،
Check out that haircut. It's a bit odd. (Laughter)
انظرو إلى هذه التسريحة. إنها غريبة بعض الشيء. (ضحك)
And at the age of 11, I was inspired by the real explorers
وفي عمر 11، تأثرت بالمستكشفين الحقيقيين
to want to try to be the first to walk to both Poles.
وأردت أن أحاول أن أكون أول من يمشي إلى كلا القطبين.
I found it incredibly inspiring
وجدته أمراً مشجعاً كثيراً
that the idea of becoming a polar traveler
بأن فكرة كوني مستكشف قطبي
went down pretty well with girls at parties when I was at university.
جرت بشكل جيد جداً مع الفتيات في الحفلات عندما كنت بالجامعة.
That was a bit more inspiring.
كان هذا مشجعاً أكثر قليلاً.
And after years, seven years of fundraising,
وبعد سنوات، 7 سنوات من جمع التبرعات
seven years of being told no,
7 سنوات من مواجهة الرفض،
seven years of being told by my family to seek counseling
7 سنوات أخبرني فيها أقاربي بأن أبحث عن الإرشاد
and psychiatric help,
والمساعدة النفسية،
eventually three of us found ourselves marching to the South Geographic Pole
في النهاية ثلاثة منا وجدنا أنفسنا نمشي إلى القطب الجنوبي الجغرافي
on the longest unassisted march ever made anywhere on Earth in history.
في أطول رحلة مشي بدون مساعدة حصلت في أي مكان من الأرض في التاريخ.
In this photograph, we are standing in an area
في هذه الصورة، نحن نقف في منطقة
the size of the United States of America,
بحجم الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
and we're on our own.
ونحن لوحدنا بالكامل.
We have no radio communications, no backup.
ليس لدينا اتصال لاسلكي، لا دعم.
Beneath our feet, 90 percent of all the world's ice,
تحت أقدامنا، 90% من كل جليد العالم.
70 percent of all the world's fresh water.
70% من كل الماء العذب في العالم.
We're standing on it.
نحن نقف عليه.
This is the power of Antarctica.
هذه هي قوة القارة القطبية الجنوبية.
On this journey, we faced the danger of crevasses,
في هذه الرحلة، واجهنا خطر الشقوق الأرضية،
intense cold,
والبرد الشديد،
so cold that sweat turns to ice inside your clothing,
شديد لدرجة أن عرقك يتحول لجليد داخل ملابسك،
your teeth can crack,
أسنانك قد تتحطم،
water can freeze in your eyes.
الماء قد يتجمد في عينيك،
Let's just say it's a bit chilly. (Laughter)
دعونا نقول إنها باردة قليلاً. (ضحك)
And after 70 desperate days, we arrive at the South Pole.
وبعد 70 يوماً من اليأس، وصلنا إلى القطب الجنوبي.
We had done it.
لقد فعلناها.
But something happened to me on that 70-day journey in 1986
لكن هناك شي حصل لي في رحلة الـ 70 يوماً تلك في عام 1986
that brought me here, and it hurt.
أحضرني إلى هنا، وآلمني.
My eyes changed color in 70 days through damage.
تغيّر لون عيني بعد 70 يوم من التضرر.
Our faces blistered out.
خرجت فقاعات من وجوهنا.
The skin ripped off and we wondered why.
تقشّر الجلد واستغربنا لذلك.
And when we got home, we were told by NASA
وعندما عدنا للوطن، أخبرتنا NASA
that a hole in the ozone had been discovered
بأنه تم اكتشاف ثقب في طبقة الأوزون
above the South Pole,
فوق القطب الجنوبي،
and we'd walked underneath it the same year it had been discovered.
وكنا نحن قد مشينا تحته في نفس العام الذي اكتشف فيه.
Ultraviolet rays down, hit the ice, bounced back, fried out the eyes,
تهبط الأشعة فوق البنفسجية، تصدم الجليد وترتد لتؤذي عيوننا،
ripped off our faces.
وتسلخ جلد وجوهنا.
It was a bit of a shock -- (Laughter) --
كانت صدمة إلى حدٍ ما (ضحك)
and it started me thinking.
وجعلني ذلك أفكر.
In 1989, we now head north.
في عام 1989، اتجهنا للشمال.
Sixty days, every step away from the safety of land
ستون يوماً، كل خطوة تبعدنا عن السلامة على اليابسة
across a frozen ocean.
عبر محيط متجمد.
It was desperately cold again.
كانت الأجواء شديدة البرودة مرة أخرى.
Here's me coming in from washing naked at -60 Celsius.
هذا أنا أدخل بعد الاغتسال عارياً في حرارة -60 مئوية.
And if anybody ever says to you, "I am cold" -- (Laughter) --
وإذا قال لكم أحد ما "أنا أشعر بالبرد"، (ضحك)
if they look like this, they are cold, definitely.
إذا بدا بهذا المنظر، فهو يشعر بالبرد حقاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And 1,000 kilometers away from the safety of land,
وعلى بعد 1000 كيلومتر عن سلامة اليابسة،
disaster strikes.
حدثت كارثة.
The Arctic Ocean melts beneath our feet four months before it ever had in history,
ذاب المحيط المتجمد الشمالي تحت أقدامنا قبل 4 أشهر مما قد حصل في التاريخ على الإطلاق،
and we're 1,000 kilometers from safety.
ونحن على بعد 1000 كيلومتر من الأمان.
The ice is crashing around us, grinding, and I'm thinking, "Are we going to die?"
يتحطم الجليد حولنا ويُطحن، وأنا أفكر، "هل سنموت؟"
But something clicked in my head on this day,
ولكن هناك شيء اتضح في ذهني في ذلك اليوم،
as I realized we, as a world, are in a survival situation,
كما تبين لي، نحن كعالم، نواجه مشكلة البقاء،
and that feeling has never gone away for 25 long years.
وهذا الإحساس لم يزُل أبداً لمدة 25 سنة طويلة.
Back then, we had to march or die.
وقتها، كان علينا أن نمشي أو أن نموت.
And we're not some TV survivor program.
ونحن لسنا ببرنامج تحدي بقاء تلفزيوني.
When things go wrong for us, it's life or death,
عندما تسوء الأمور بالنسبة لنا، إنها مسألة حياة أو موت،
and our brave African-American Daryl,
وزميلنا الشجاع الإفريقي-الأمريكي داريل،
who would become the first American to walk to the North Pole,
والذي سيصبح أول أمريكي يمشي إلى القطب الشمالي،
his heel dropped off from frostbite 200 klicks out.
سقط كعب قدمه من التجمد على بعد 200 كيلومتر.
He must keep going, he does,
عليه أن يستمر، فعلاً،
and after 60 days on the ice, we stood at the North Pole.
وبعد 60 يوماً على الجليد، وقفنا عند القطب الشمالي.
We had done it.
لقد فعلناها.
Yes, I became the first person in history stupid enough to walk to both Poles,
نعم، أصبحت أول شخص في التاريخ غبي لدرجة أن يمشي إلى كلا القطبين،
but it was our success.
لكنه كان نجاحنا جميعاً.
And sadly, on return home,
وللأسف، عند العودة للوطن،
it was not all fun.
لم يكن الأمر ممتعاً دائماً.
I became very low.
أصبحت محبطاً جداً.
To succeed at something is often harder than actually making it happen.
النجاح في شيء ما هو غالباً أصعب من الوصول إليه.
I was empty, lonely, financially destroyed.
لقد كنت محبطاً ووحيداً ومدمراً مالياً.
I was without hope,
كنت يائساً،
but hope came in the form of the great Jacques Cousteau,
ولكن الأمل جاء على هيئة الشخص العظيم جاك كوستو،
and he inspired me to take on the 2041 mission.
وقد ألهمني بأن آخذ على عاتقي المهمة 2041.
Being Jacques, he gave me clear instructions:
كونه جاك، أعطاني نصائح واضحة:
Engage the world leaders, talk to industry and business,
اجذب اهتمام قادة العالم، تحدث إلى الصناعيين والتجار،
and above all, Rob, inspire young people,
وفوق كل ذلك يا روب، عليك بتوعية الشباب،
because they will choose the future of the preservation of Antarctica.
لأنهم سيحددون مستقبل الحفاظ على القطب الجنوبي.
For the world leaders, we've been to every world Earth Summit,
وبالنسبة لقادة العالم، ذهبنا إلى كل قمة من قمم الأرض العالمية،
all three of them, with our brave yacht, 2041,
الثلاثة جميعهم، مع يختنا الممتاز المسمى 2041،
twice to Rio, once in '92, once in 2012,
مرتان إلى ريو ديجانيرو، مرة في عام 1992، ومرة أخرى عام 2012،
and for the Earth Summit in Johannesburg,
وإلى قمة الأرض في جوهانسبورغ،
we made the longest overland voyage ever made with a yacht,
لقد قمنا بأطول رحلة يخت على البر حصلت على الإطلاق،
13,000 kilometers around the whole of Southern Africa
13000 كيلومتر حول كل إفريقيا الجنوبية
doing our best to inspire over a million young people in person
قمنا بأفضل ما لدينا لتوعية أكثر من مليون شاب شخصياً
about 2041 and about their environment.
عن 2041 وعن بيئتهم.
For the last 11 years, we have taken over 1,000 people,
خلال الـ 11 سنة الماضية، أخذنا أكثر من 1000 شخص،
people from industry and business, women and men from companies,
أشخاصاً من الصناعة والتجارة، رجال ونساء من الشركات،
students from all over the world, down to Antarctica,
وطلاباً من كل أنحاء العالم إلى القطب الجنوبي،
and during those missions, we've managed to pull out
وخلال هذه المهمات استطعنا أن نستخرج
over 1,500 tons of twisted metal left in Antarctica.
أكثر من 1500 طن من المعادن الملتوية متروكة في القطب الجنوبي.
That took eight years, and I'm so proud of it
استغرق ذلك 8 سنوات، وأنا فخور جداً بذلك
because we recycled all of it back here in South America.
لأننا قمنا بإعادة تصنيعها كلها هنا في أمريكا الجنوبية.
I have been inspired ever since I could walk
تعلمت منذ أن استطعت المشي
to recycle by my mum.
بأن أعيد تصنيع الأشياء بواسطة أمي.
Here she is, and my mum --
ها هي، وأمي..
(Applause) --
(تصفيق)
my mum is still recycling,
وأمي ما زالت تعيد التصنيع،
and as she is in her 100th year, isn't that fantastic?
وهي في عامها المائة، أليس ذلك مدهشٌ؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And when -- I love my mum.
وعندما -- أنا أحب أمي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But when Mum was born,
ولكن عندما ولدت أمي،
the population of our planet was only 1.8 billion people,
كان تعداد سكان كوكبنا 1.8 مليار فقط،
and talking in terms of billions,
وبالحديث عن المليارات،
we have taken young people from industry and business
أخذنا الشباب من الصناعة والتجارة
from India, from China.
من الهند والصين.
These are game-changing nations, and will be hugely important
هذه الدول تغير قواعد اللعبة، وستكون ذات أهمية كبرى
in the decision about the preservation of the Antarctic.
في قرار الحفاظ على القطب الجنوبي.
Unbelievably, we've engaged and inspired women to come from the Middle East,
بشكل لا يصدق، شاركنا ولفتنا انتباه نساء بأن يأتوا من الشرق الأوسط
often for the first time they've represented their nations in Antarctica.
غالباً للمرة الأولى مثلن دولهنّ في القطب الجنوبي.
Fantastic people, so inspired.
أشخاص عظيمون، ملهمين كثيراً.
To look after Antarctica,
كي تعتني بالقارة القطبية الجنوبية،
you've got to first engage people with this extraordinary place,
عليك أولاً أن تشارك الناس بهذا المكان غير الاعتيادي،
form a relationship, form a bond,
شكل علاقةً، شكل رابطةً،
form some love.
شكل بعض الحب.
It is such a privilege to go to Antarctica,
إنها لمزية حقاً أن تذهب إلى القطب الجنوبي،
I can't tell you.
لا يمكنني أن أخبركم.
I feel so lucky,
أشعر بأني محظوظ جداً،
and I've been 35 times in my life,
وقد ذهبت 35 مرة في حياتي،
and all those people who come with us return home as great champions,
وكل الناس الذين يأتون معنا يعودون إلى بلادهم كأبطال عظيمين،
not only for Antarctica,
ليس فقط من أجل القطب الجنوبي،
but for local issues back in their own nations.
ولكن من أجل القضايا المحلية في أوطانهم.
Let's go back to where we began: the ice melt of the North and South Poles.
دعونا نعود من حيث بدأنا: ذوبان جليد القطبين الشمالي والجنوبي.
And it's not good news.
إنه ليس بخبر سار.
NASA informed us six months ago
أبلغتنا ناسا قبل ستة أشهر
that the Western Antarctic Ice Shelf is now disintegrating.
بأن الحيد الجليدي الغربي في القطب الجنوبي بدأ يتفكك.
Huge areas of ice --
مساحات ضخمة من الجليد --
look how big Antarctica is even compared to here --
انظروا إلى حجم القطب الجنوبي حتى بالمقارنة مع هنا --
Huge areas of ice are breaking off from Antarctica,
مساحات ضخمة من الجليد تنفصل عن القطب الجنوبي،
the size of small nations.
بحجم دول صغيرة.
And NASA have calculated that the sea level will rise,
وقدرت ناسا بأن مستوى البحر سوف يرتفع،
it is definite,
إنه أمر مؤكد،
by one meter in the next 100 years,
سيرتفع بمقدار متر واحد خلال الـ 100 عام القادمة،
the same time that my mum has been on planet Earth.
نفس المدة التي عاشتها أمي على كوكب الأرض.
It's going to happen,
سوف يحدث ذلك،
and I've realized that the preservation of Antarctica
وأنا أدركت بأن الحفاظ على القارة القطبية الجنوبية
and our survival here on Earth are linked.
وبقاؤنا هنا على كوكب الأرض مرتبطان.
And there is a very simple solution.
وهناك حل بسيط جداً.
If we are using more renewable energy in the real world,
إذا استخدمنا مزيداً من الطاقة المتجددة في العالم الحقيقي،
if we are being more efficient with the energy here,
إذا استخدمنا الطاقة بكفاءة أكبر هنا،
running our energy mix in a cleaner way,
واستعملنا مزيج الطاقة بطريقة أنظف،
there will be no financial reason to go and exploit Antarctica.
لن يكون هناك سبب مالي للذهاب واستغلال القطب الجنوبي.
It won't make financial sense,
لن يكون ذلك مجدياً مادياً،
and if we manage our energy better, we also may be able to slow down,
وإذا تعاملنا مع طاقتنا بشكل أفضل، قد نتمكن أيضاً من إبطاء،
maybe even stop,
وربما إيقاف،
this great ice melt that threatens us.
هذا الذوبان الهائل الذي يهددنا.
It's a big challenge, and what is our response to it?
إنه تحدٍ كبير، وما هي ردة فعلنا تجاهه؟
We've got to go back one last time,
علينا أن نعود مرة أخيرة،
and at the end of next year,
وفي نهاية العام القادم،
we will go back to the South Geographic Pole,
سوف نعود إلى القطب الجنوبي الجغرافي،
where we arrived 30 years ago on foot,
إلى حيث ذهبنا مشياً على الأقدام قبل 30 عاماً،
and retrace our steps of 1,600 kilometers,
ونتبع الخطى التي مشيناها لمسافة 1600 كيلومتر،
but this time only using renewable energy to survive.
ولكن هذه المرة باستخدام الطاقة المتجددة فقط للبقاء.
We will walk across those icecaps, which far down below are melting,
سوف نمشي عبر تلك القمم الجليدية التي تذوب بالعمق،
hopefully inspiring some solutions on that issue.
متأملين بأن نكون مصدر إلهام لحلول لتلك القضية.
This is my son, Barney.
هذا ابني، بارني.
He is coming with me.
سوف يذهب معي.
He is committed to walking side by side with his father,
تعهّد بالمشي بجانب أبيه،
and what he will do is to translate these messages
وما سيفعله هو ترجمة هذه الرسائل
and inspire these messages to the minds of future young leaders.
وإيصال هذه الرسائل إلى عقول قادة المستقبل الشباب.
I'm extremely proud of him.
أنا فخور جداً به.
Good on him, Barney.
عظيم جداً يا بارني.
Ladies and gentlemen, a survivor -- and I'm good --
سيداتي سادتي، الشخص الناجي -- وأنا كذلك --
a survivor sees a problem and doesn't go, "Whatever."
الشخص الناجي يرى المشكلة ولا يقول "أياً كان."
A survivor sees a problem and deals with that problem
الشخص الناجي يرى المشكلة ويتعامل معها
before it becomes a threat.
قبل أن تشكل تهديداً.
We have 27 years to preserve the Antarctic.
لدينا 27 عاماً لنحافظ على القطب الجنوبي.
We all own it.
إنه ملكنا جميعاً.
We all have responsibility.
جميعنا مسؤولون.
The fact that nobody owns it maybe means that we can succeed.
حقيقة أنه ليس ملكاً لأحد قد تعني أننا سننجح.
Antarctica is a moral line in the snow,
القطب الجنوبي هو خط أخلاقي في الثلج،
and on one side of that line we should fight,
وعلى أحد جانبي الخط علينا أن نناضل،
fight hard for this one beautiful, pristine place left alone on Earth.
نناضل كثيراً من أجل هذا المكان الوحيد الجميل وغير المفسد المتبقي على الأرض.
I know it's possible.
أنا متأكد بأن ذلك ممكن.
We are going to do it.
سوف نقوم بذلك.
And I'll leave you with these words from Goethe.
وسأترككم بهذه الكلمات من غوته.
I've tried to live by them.
أحاول بأن أتبعها في حياتي.
"If you can do, or dream you can,
"إذا كان بإمكانك أن تفعل، أو أن تحلم،
begin it now,
ابدأ بذلك الآن،
for boldness has genius, power and magic in it."
لأن الشجاعة فيها طاقة وسحر عبقريان."
Good luck to you all.
حظاً سعيداً لكم جميعاً.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)